Changes in your diet not
only affect you physically,
physiologically inside,
but also mentally,
how well you think,
psychologically,
how well you feel.
But you’ll never know just
how good you can feel
until you put it to the test
and try eating healthy.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the relationship
between diet and inflammation.
And we start with a story
about the best ways
to alleviate chronic
pain syndromes.
Fibromyalgia is a common disorder
whose cardinal manifestation
is chronic, widespread pain.
Well, not so common, affecting
2 to 4% of the population
though probably more like
2%, and especially women.
For decades, some medical
professionals dismissed fibromyalgia
as all in people’s heads, but this
outdated view has been refuted
by more recent research
characterizing it as a disorder
of pain regulation and sensitization.
Brain imaging studies have shown
several perturbations of pain
processing and regulation
that amplify pain
in people with the condition.
Twin studies have shown that about
half of fibromyalgia is genetic,
but the other half we
can do something about.
There are lots of drugs with
lots of side effects to help
with some of the symptoms, but
what about lifestyle approaches?
Engagement in regular
physical activity is considered
imperative for effective
management of ﬁbromyalgia.
A systematic review
and meta-analysis
of randomized clinical
trials on the
effectiveness of therapeutic
exercise in fibromyalgia
found that both aerobic
and resistance exercises
are effective ways of reducing pain
and improving global well-being
in people with fibromyalgia.
Patients may worry and
perceive that exercise
will worsen their pain and fatigue,
and so you have to start slow and
work your way up as tolerated,
with the goal of eventually
achieving 30 to 60 minutes
of moderate intensity aerobic
exercise in addition to
muscle strengthening exercises
(1 to 3 sets of 8–11 exercises,
8–10 repetitions with
a load of about 7 pounds
or 45% of the max you can lift.
But what about dietary
interventions in terms of
dialing down the pain sensitivity?
Well, what causes it in the
first place? Inflammation.
During the inﬂammatory response,
pain receptors are activated,
and chronic inflammation,
can cause chronic activation,
which may cause chronic
pain, due to this prolonged
hypersensitization
of pain pathways.
No wonder, then, that
a pro-inﬂammatory diet
was found to be associated
with pain hypersensitivity
in patients with
fibromyalgia syndrome.
Exactly which foods
are pro-inflammatory
and which foods
are anti-inflammatory?
Check out those twin videos,
but broadly speaking
components of processed
foods and animal products,
such as saturated fat,
trans fat, and cholesterol,
were found to be
pro-inflammatory,
while constituents
of whole plant foods,
such as fiber and phytonutrients,
were strongly anti-inflammatory.
The intake of dietary fiber,
found concentrated in
only one place—
whole plant foods—
is fundamental to reducing not
only the risk of abdominal pain
but also muscle and joint pain,
we think because of these
short chain fatty acids
that our good gut bugs
produce when we eat fiber.
These short chain fatty acids
are important mediators of pain,
fundamentally because
they modulate inﬂammation.
So having a lot of fiber-feeding
bugs in your colon is like
carrying around your own anti-
inflammatory compound factory.
But to cultivate them you actually
have to eat the
foods that feed them.
And in terms of phytonutrients,
plant-derived polyphenols
are widely acknowledged to also
act as anti-inﬂammatory substances.
Here’s some foods packed with
anti-pain pathway nutrients:
berries, greens, citrus, nuts,
spices like turmeric and ginger,
edamame, and green tea.
That’s why you can do randomized,
double-blind crossover trials
showing that about three cups
worth of strawberries a day
can significantly improve
pain and inflammation.
If that’s what a
single plant can do,
what about a diet chock
full of plant foods?
Put people on a strictly
plant-based diet rich in
fresh fruits and vegetables, whole
grains and various legumes,
which are beans, split peas,
chickpeas, and lentils,
as well as nuts and
seeds, and you can drop
C-reactive protein
levels 33% in 3 weeks,
which is a leading blood marker
of systemic inflammation.
But does that translate
into less pain?
And the answer is yes, when it
comes to migraine headaches.
Yes when it comes
to painful periods.
A signiﬁcant reduction in menstrual
pain, duration of pain, intensity
in addition to
premenstrual symptoms.
In fact even just a
single plant, cinnamon,
about a third of a teaspoon three
times a day during your period
can help, though it doesn’t
work as well as ibuprofen.
Ginger powder,
on the other hand—
ground ginger – has been found
to be comparable to
ibuprofen in relieving pain
in women with painful cramps.
You can learn more in
my video on the topic.
Whole-food plant-based
diets also alleviate
the symptoms of osteoarthritis.
Several studies have shown
improvements in rheumatoid arthritis
symptoms with diets
excluding animal products,
though it may be just
as much a function of
increasing the quantity
of healthy plant foods.
But it’s not just because plant-
based diets are so effective
in causing weight loss,
even at the same weight
there’s an improvement
in rheumatoid arthritis
from more plant-based diets.
And plant-based diets can also
alleviate fibromyalgia symptoms.
This is the latest study,
which enrolled anyone
with chronic musculoskeletal
pain, fibromyalgia or not.
Yes, diets high in animal proteins
and fats have been linked to
chronic pain and inﬂammation,
while plant-based diets
produce anti-inﬂammatory responses.
So, did it actually work when
put to the test for pain?
Yes.
Consumption of a
plant-based diet produced
positive improvements
in chronic pain and function.
How much?
Well, a minimally clinically
important diﬀerence in
chronic musculoskeletal
pain is 1 point on the
Numeric Pain Rating Scale,
which is just a scale of 1 to 10,
on how much pain you’re feeling.
And on the plant-based diet
perceived pain
decreased an average of
three points on
a 10-point scale,
from an average of 5 or
6 out of 10 down to 2.
Now, unlike most of prior studies
there was no control group,
but what’s the downside of
giving healthier eating a try?
In fact, those with chronic pain
are more likely to be overweight
and have nutrition-related maladies
such as high blood pressure,
diabetes, and heart disease
all of which can be prevented,
arrested, and in some
cases even reversed
with a healthy-enough
plant-based diet.
So, any pain benefit is just
icing on the cake of health.
Uh...scratch that.
How about...
the dollop of guacamole
on your bean burrito.
In our next story,
we look at how plant based
diets may be effective
in the treatment
of fibromyalgia—
a condition suffered
by millions.
According to the latest review
on fibromyalgia and nutrition,
a vegetarian diet could have
some beneficial effects,
but based on what kind of evidence?
Well, back in 1991,
a survey was sent
to a few hundred folks suffering
from various chronic pain conditions
including fibromyalgia,
asking if they found any success
trying different diets.
Some folks tried a vegetarian diet,
some folks tried a vegan diet.
Some reported the various diets
helped with pain, stiffness, and swelling.
Vegan diets were reported
to reduce disease symptoms
more effectively than the vegetarian diet
with rheumatoid arthritis.
But what we needed was to put these diets
to the test in formal studies.
The first one was in ’93.
Ten fibromyalgia patients were put on
a vegetarian diet for three weeks.
The measured levels of oxidation
and inflammation and cholesterol went down
– no surprise.
But of interest
from a clinical point of view
is the positive effect of the treatment
upon pain status of most of the patients.
Seven out of ten felt better.
They weren’t sure
if it was the improved condition
of the fibromyalgia patients
in this course of treatment
with a vegetarian diet –
whether it was due to the improvement
of their antioxidant status
or what it was about a meat-free diet
that seemed to help so much.
A vegan diet was first put to the test
in 2000, in Helsinki.
You can tell English is not the researchers’
first language with sentences like:
“Plants face heavy load of light.”
The point they’re making is good though.
UV light generates free radicals
in their tissues.
All this means is that, you know,
plants must be well prepared
to meet the challenges
of the oxidant radical stress
and contain a broad variety
of antioxidants.
That’s why plants don’t get sunburned
and their DNA damaged
hanging out all day in the sun
without any sun block on.
So what would happen if you had people
live exclusively on plant items?
In other words, what might be the effects
of a strict vegan diet
on the symptoms of fibromyalgia?
In fact the study used a raw vegan diet.
The rheumatoid patients said
they felt better
when they started to eat
the living food diet,
and the symptoms got worse
when they returned back
to their previous omnivorous diet.
But what about the fibromyalgia patients?
Both groups reported having
quite a lot of pain at rest
in the beginning of the study.
But there’s a significant decrease
in the raw vegan group,
which gradually disappeared
after shifting back to the omnivorous diet.
They also found other
significant changes,
such as improvement
in the quality of sleep,
reduction of morning stiffness,
and improvement in measures
of general health.
They started out about the same,
but after about a month and a half
those eating vegan felt
significantly less stiff,
which continued through the end
of the three-month study.
And when they went back to eating their
regular diet, the stiffness returned.
What about pains at rest?
Same thing.
So significant improvements
in fibromyalgia –
stiffness, pain, and general health
on a plant-based diet.
The study only lasted three months,
but it can be concluded that eating vegan
has beneficial effects
on fibromyalgia symptoms,
at least in the short run.
Finally today,
we look at a study that suggests
chocolate may improve symptoms
for those suffering from
chronic fatigue syndrome.
Chronic fatigue syndrome is a
debilitating condition characterized by
a minimum of six months of crushing
mental and physical exhaustion,
and we have no idea what causes it.
We don’t even have a good idea
of how many people even have it.
The Centers for Disease Control
estimates that as many as
seven and a half million Americans
currently suffer from it.
And we as physicians have
very little to offer patients
in terms of relieving those symptoms.
So, this is one of the conditions that
I’m always keeping an eye out for
in terms of new treatments.
And one of the latest they
just discovered?
Chocolate.
Evidently, Montezuma the Second,
who reigned the Aztec empire
500 years ago, noted:
“This divine drink, which builds
up resistance, and fights fatigue.
A cup of [cocoa] permits people to
walk for a whole day without food.’’
Not willing to take the emperor’s
word for it, it was put to the test.
I’m always skeptical of
industry-supported research,
but it was actually a pretty good study.
At first glance, it looked like
they were basically saying eat
three chocolate bars a day for eight
weeks, and call me in the morning.
But it was actually a randomized,
double-blind, placebo-controlled
crossover trial, which is about
as good as you can get.
The mad scientists over at Nestle took
white chocolate, dyed it brown, and then
added some sort of fake chocolate
flavor, such that people couldn’t tell if
they were eating the
real chocolate or the fake.
Comparable amounts of sugar and fat,
but one had cocoa solids—
phytonutrients—and the
other basically didn’t.
So, they were able to put people on one,
and then switch them over,
without anyone knowing,
to see if their chronic fatigue
symptoms got better or worse.
And there was a
significant improvement
in the real chocolate group,
meaning it apparently wasn’t just
the yummy taste of chocolate, but the
action of the cacao phytonutrients.
Of course, no one should be eating
three chocolate bars a day,
but you can get the equivalent
dose of cocoa solids,
the equivalent dose of those
wonderful cocoa phytonutrients,
by consuming two and a half
tablespoons of cocoa powder a day.
You can put it in coffee,
you can make a chocolaty smoothie,
or, my personal favorite,
you can blend it in a high-speed blender
with frozen cherries or strawberries,
a touch of non-dairy milk,
vanilla extract, and some
erythritol or some dates,
and you have instant, decadent
chocolate ice cream; low-fat,
low-calorie, no cholesterol,
no added sugar chocolate ice cream.
The more you eat,
the healthier you are—
whether or not you’re suffering
from chronic fatigue.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.